"Side Effects of Metformin
as a Life-Extension Drug"
The apparent
reductions in mortality
from all causes put together
and diseases of aging
associated with metformin use
suggest that the drug metformin
could be extending
life and healthspans
by acting as a geroprotective,
or anti-aging, agent.
What might the downsides be?
Gastrointestinal side-effects,
such as flatulence,
indigestion,
and abdominal discomfort,
are relatively common.
More than half
starting metformin
report diarrhea, for example,
and a quarter experience
nausea or vomiting.
About 10 percent
unknowingly taking the placebo
report similar symptoms, though;
so, the actual
proportion of people
suffering such symptoms
due to the drug
is probably more like 1 in 3.
Most of these effects
tend to be transient, though,
and can be minimized
by taking metformin with food
and starting
at a suboptimal dose,
increasing gradually to target
over a period of weeks.
Once-a-day
extended-release versions
also tend to be more tolerable.
The most dreaded
side effect, though,
is lactic acidosis,
the potentially fatal buildup
of acid in the blood.
I mean,
poisoning of the mitochondria
is kind of the whole point.
That's what activates AMPK,
but it's supposed to be a mild
mitochondrial poison,
but sometimes it evidently
poisons a bit too much.
Thankfully,
metformin-induced
lactic acidosis
is extremely rare.
It has a fatality rate
of 50 percent
but only occurs
at a rate of about
0.03 cases
per thousand patient-years.
That means
taking metformin for a year
only has about a 1 in 67,000
chance of killing you.
Lactic acidosis
is primarily caused
by insufficient metformin
clearance by the kidneys;
so, risk can be minimized by,
for example,
temporarily stopping the drug
while undergoing procedures
that put the kidneys at risk,
such as major surgery
or intravenous contrast dyes
used for certain
imaging procedures.
Those with
mild to moderate kidney disease
can still benefit from metformin
at an adjusted dose.
Elderly individuals
should have their
kidney function tested
before starting metformin,
and regularly monitored.
Excess alcohol consumption
is also believed
to increase the risk
of fatal metformin-induced
lactic acidosis.
One of the more
insidious side effects
is B12 deficiency,
vitamin B12 deficiency,
affecting as many
as one in three
long-term metformin users,
but can start
as early as a few months.
The mechanism is still unclear,
but routine monitoring of B12
status has been recommended,
and B12 supplementation
has been suggested.
Another adverse consequence
of metformin
is less side effect
than main effect.
Remember how metformin
is a mild mitochondrial poison?
The way metformin boosts AMPK
is by impairing our body's
ability to produce energy.
What might that mean
for athletic performance?
Healthy men and women
were found to suffer
a significant decline
in peak aerobic capacity
after only about
a week on metformin.
The average hit was only
three percent, though,
which could be meaningful
for an elite athlete
but would be unlikely to impede
recreational physical activity.
However, some individuals
lost as much as 10 percent,
which could
be noticeably fatiguing.
Note these detriments
were only found
at or near maximal workloads,
and so, most active individuals
would be unlikely
to experience an impairment
in routine activity.
Over the long term, though,
metformin may undercut
physical fitness.
Older adults were randomized
to 12 weeks
of supervised aerobic exercise
on or off metformin.
They trained for 45 minutes
three times a week
on a treadmill,
bike, or elliptical,
ramping up to a vigorous target
of 85 percent
of their maximal heart rate.
Unfortunately, metformin
attenuated the improvement
in physiological function
after exercise training.
Cardiovascular fitness
is so important;
yet, after three months,
metformin cut their improvement
in cardiorespiratory fitness
in half compared to placebo,
though this didn't reach
statistical significance.
Metformin did, however,
significantly
blunt their improvement
in whole-body
insulin sensitivity
which normally improves
with physical activity.
Aerobic exercise, (or "cardio")
is critical for maintaining
cardiovascular fitness,
whereas resistance exercise
(also known
as strength training,
for example,
with weights or bands)
is essential for maintaining
muscle mass as we age.
In 2019,
the so-called MASTERS trial
was published,
investigating what metformin
might do to muscle gains,
and, the title of the paper
gives it away:
"Metformin blunts
muscle hypertrophy
in response to progressive
resistance exercise training
in older adults."
After 14 weeks of progressive
resistance training,
men and women
in the placebo group
accrued significant
lean body mass,
but those randomized
to the metformin group did not.
For example,
about a four percent gain
in thigh muscle mass
in the placebo group
versus virtually none
in the metformin group.
The differences
in strength, however,
did not reach
statistical significance.
So, might the benefits
of metformin
outweigh the risks for expanding
the healthspan and lifespan
of even nondiabetics?
The investigators
reviewing the evidence
that diabetics
taking metformin lived longer,
on average, than nondiabetics,
concluded their
"results suggest that metformin
could be an effective
intervention
to extend
the lifespan of people
who do not have diabetes."
You can't know, though,
until you put it to the test,
which I'll explore, next.